<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc8174 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc7515 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc4122 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml">
]>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-rosie-framework-03"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ROSIE Framework">ROSIE: Regulated Object Structure for Intelligent Evidence</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-rosie-framework-03"/>
    <author fullname="Jane Doe" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Doe">
      <organization>ROSIE Working Group</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jd@example.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="2" day="7"/>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <workgroup>ROSIE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>GxP</keyword>
    <keyword>AI Agent</keyword>
    <keyword>Validation</keyword>
    <keyword>Compliance</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines ROSIE (Regulated Object Structure for Intelligent Evidence), a framework for self-validating AI-generated software. It specifies a machine-readable repository structure, a hierarchical documentation model, and a cryptographic evidence protocol. ROSIE enables autonomous agents to maintain GxP compliance (e.g., 21 CFR Part 11) by treating validation artifacts as first-class, version-controlled objects. ROSIE defines the artifact format and evidence protocol; for agent behavioral instructions, compliance gates, and workflow modes, see the GxP.MD specification (https://gxp.md).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Traditional software validation in regulated industries (GxP) relies on manual, retrospective documentation. In agent-led development, this model fails to scale. ROSIE provides a protocol for "Continuous Validation," where an AI agent acts as a trusted maintainer of a cryptographically verifiable V-Model.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="repo_structure">
      <name>Repository Structure and State Consistency</name>
      <t>A ROSIE-compliant repository MUST maintain the following structure:</t>
      <sourcecode type="ascii-art">
/
├── GxP.MD                   # Compliance Instructions (GxP.MD standard)
├── .gxp/                    # Quality Management System Root
│   ├── system_context.md    # Apex Document (Desired State)
│   ├── risk_assessment.log  # Deterministic Risk Log
│   ├── adr/                 # Architecture Decisions
│   ├── requirements/        # OPTIONAL: Formal REQ-NNN.md documents
│   ├── user_stories/        # OPTIONAL: Formal US-NNN-NNN.md documents
│   ├── specs/               # OPTIONAL: Formal SPEC-NNN-NNN.md documents
│   └── evidence/            # Signed Validation Artifacts
└── src/                     # Implementation &amp; Design Specs
      </sourcecode>
      <t>When a project uses GxP.MD as its compliance instruction standard, the GxP.MD file at the project root defines the regulatory context, risk matrix, annotation requirements, gate definitions, and agent behavioral directives. The .gxp/ directory contains artifacts, evidence, and project-level documents. Formal artifact files in .gxp/requirements/, .gxp/user_stories/, and .gxp/specs/ are OPTIONAL when the project uses annotation-first traceability as defined by GxP.MD v2.</t>

      <section anchor="consistency">
        <name>State Consistency and Concurrency</name>
        <t>To ensure integrity during multi-agent or human-agent collaboration, the repository MUST utilize atomic commits. The .gxp/ directory acts as the authoritative state. An agent MUST NOT update source code without a corresponding increment to the version field in system_context.md if the change impacts intended use.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="risk_assessment_log">
        <name>Risk Assessment Log Format</name>
        <t>The file .gxp/risk_assessment.log MUST be a deterministic, append-only risk register in Markdown format. Each entry MUST conform to the following structure:</t>
        <sourcecode type="markdown">
## RISK-{NNN}: {Title}

- **Date:** YYYY-MM-DD
- **Author:** author@example.com
- **Component:** path/to/affected/code
- **Risk Level:** HIGH | MEDIUM | LOW
- **Description:** What risk was identified.
- **Impact:** What could go wrong if the risk materializes.
- **Mitigation:** Controls in place to reduce the risk.
- **Status:** open | mitigated | accepted | closed
        </sourcecode>
        <t>Fields:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>RISK-NNN: Unique sequential identifier. Infrastructure risks MAY use RISK-INF-NNN.</li>
          <li>Date: ISO 8601 date (YYYY-MM-DD) when the risk was identified.</li>
          <li>Author: Email or identifier of the person who identified the risk.</li>
          <li>Component: File path or module affected by the risk.</li>
          <li>Risk Level: One of LOW, MEDIUM, or HIGH per the Risk Matrix Taxonomy in Section 4.</li>
          <li>Description: What was identified as a risk.</li>
          <li>Impact: Free-text description of the potential negative outcome.</li>
          <li>Mitigation: Free-text description of the controls in place.</li>
          <li>Status: One of "open" (unresolved), "mitigated" (controls in place), "accepted" (risk acknowledged), or "closed" (risk no longer applies).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Agents MUST append a new risk entry whenever a requirement is added or modified, or when a new risk vector is identified (new external dependency, new data flow involving PHI, changes to authentication logic). Existing entries MUST NOT be deleted; superseded risks SHOULD have their status set to "closed" with a reference to the superseding entry.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="adr_directory">
        <name>Architecture Decision Records</name>
        <t>The directory .gxp/adr/ MUST contain Architecture Decision Records (ADRs) for all significant technical decisions. Each ADR MUST be a Markdown file named ADR-NNN-short-title.md and MUST contain at minimum:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Title: Descriptive name of the decision.</li>
          <li>Status: One of "Proposed", "Accepted", "Deprecated", or "Superseded".</li>
          <li>Context: The circumstances and constraints that led to the decision.</li>
          <li>Decision: The chosen approach.</li>
          <li>Consequences: Positive and negative impacts of the decision.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>ADRs are immutable once accepted. If a decision is reversed, a new ADR MUST be created that references the superseded ADR.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="apex">
      <name>The Apex Document: System Context</name>
      <t>The file .gxp/system_context.md defines the system boundary. It MUST contain a YAML frontmatter block adhering to the following schema:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>id: UUID (<xref target="RFC4122"/>)</li>
        <li>project_name: String</li>
        <li>version: SemVer 2.0.0</li>
        <li>gxp_risk_rating: ["LOW", "MEDIUM", "HIGH"]</li>
        <li>validation_status: ["draft", "in_review", "validated", "retired"]</li>
        <li>intended_use: String</li>
      </ul>

      <section anchor="risk_taxonomy">
        <name>Risk Matrix Taxonomy</name>
        <t>Agents SHALL determine risk based on the following taxonomy:</t>
        <ul>
          <li><strong>HIGH:</strong> Direct impact on patient safety, product quality, or PHI.</li>
          <li><strong>MEDIUM:</strong> Indirect impact; manages critical metadata or workflow.</li>
          <li><strong>LOW:</strong> No impact on GxP data integrity (e.g., UI formatting).</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="traceability">
      <name>Traceability and Documentation</name>
      <t>ROSIE traceability MUST be maintained via a "Traceability Chain" linking three levels:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Level 1 (REQ): High-level requirements. Identified as REQ-NNN.</li>
        <li>Level 2 (US): User stories with Acceptance Criteria. Identified as US-NNN-NNN. MUST link to a parent REQ.</li>
        <li>Level 3 (SPEC): Technical design/specification. Identified as SPEC-NNN-NNN. MUST link to a parent US.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>Traceability MAY be maintained through either mechanism:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>Annotation-first (GxP.MD v2 model): Traceability is expressed through structured code annotations (@gxp-req, @gxp-spec, @gxp-risk in source files; @gxp-spec, @trace, @test-type, @gxp-risk in test files). The ID scheme encodes parent-child relationships: US-001-xxx belongs to REQ-001; SPEC-001-xxx belongs to US-001-xxx. Formal artifact files in .gxp/ are OPTIONAL depth.</li>
        <li>Document-first (legacy model): Traceability is expressed through separate REQ, US, and SPEC Markdown documents with parent_id fields in YAML frontmatter. Each child document references its parent by ID.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Projects using GxP.MD as their compliance instruction standard SHOULD use the annotation-first model. Both models produce equivalent traceability chains; the annotation model eliminates drift between documentation and code.</t>

      <section anchor="error_handling">
        <name>Error Handling for Broken Links</name>
        <t>An "Invalid State" occurs if an annotation or document references a non-existent parent ID. In the annotation-first model, orphan annotations (IDs that resolve to no corresponding annotation in another file or formal artifact) are detected during the pre-merge gate and during harden mode compliance sweeps. In the document-first model, agents MUST perform a "Traceability Audit" prior to every commit. In both models, broken links MUST be resolved before merging to the main branch.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verification">
      <name>Verification Tiering (IQ/OQ/PQ)</name>
      <t>Verification activities MUST be categorized:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>IQ: Installation/Infrastructure verification.</li>
        <li>OQ: Operational/Functional (Unit/Integration) testing.</li>
        <li>PQ: Performance/E2E testing against Intended Use.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Test code MUST use the @trace annotation to link to a US-ID.</t>

      <section anchor="evidence_package_format">
        <name>Evidence Package Format</name>
        <t>Evidence MUST be produced as self-contained, tiered evidence packages stored under .gxp/evidence/. Each package is a directory whose name follows the pattern {TIER}-{SPEC_ID}-{ISO_TIMESTAMP}. A package MUST contain the following common files:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>metadata.json: Package identity including @context, package_id, spec_id, tier, traced_user_story, system_state_hash, git_commit, and created_at.</li>
          <li>environment.json: Runtime environment snapshot (node version, platform, arch, OS release, hostname, working directory, filtered environment variables, and capture timestamp).</li>
          <li>test-output.log: Human-readable test execution log with pass/fail/skip counts and per-test-case results.</li>
          <li>artifacts/test-results.json: Machine-readable test results (tool, version, passed, failed, skipped, duration_ms, test_cases array).</li>
          <li>configuration/: Directory reserved for configuration snapshots.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Tier-specific content:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>IQ packages MUST include artifacts/dependency-tree.json (resolved dependency graph) and artifacts/health-check.json (infrastructure readiness report).</li>
          <li>OQ packages MUST include artifacts/coverage-report.json (code coverage metrics with line, branch, and function percentages).</li>
          <li>PQ packages MUST include screenshots/ (PNG captures at desktop, tablet, and mobile viewports) and traces/ (Playwright trace archives for replay and debugging).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>After all files are written, a manifest.json MUST be generated listing every file in the package (excluding manifest.json and signature.jws) with its relative path, SHA-256 hash, and size in bytes. The manifest MUST include total_size_bytes and file_count. The manifest MUST then be signed to produce signature.jws per Section 7.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gxp_tag_syntax">
        <name>GxP Tag Annotation Syntax</name>
        <t>All test files and source files that participate in the evidence chain MUST include GxP annotations in JSDoc or block-comment format. Source files and test files use overlapping but distinct annotation sets.</t>
        <t>Source file annotations:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>@gxp-req REQ-XXX "Title": Links the function or module to a high-level requirement. REQUIRED on all source files implementing GxP functionality.</li>
          <li>@gxp-spec SPEC-XXX-YYY "Title": Links the function or module to a technical specification. REQUIRED on all source files implementing GxP functionality.</li>
          <li>@gxp-risk HIGH|MEDIUM|LOW: Declares the risk level. REQUIRED on all annotated source files.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Test file annotations:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>@gxp-spec SPEC-XXX-YYY: Links the test suite to the specification it verifies. REQUIRED on all test files.</li>
          <li>@trace US-XXX-YYY: Links the test suite to the user story it validates. REQUIRED on all test files.</li>
          <li>@test-type IQ|OQ|PQ: Declares the verification tier. REQUIRED on all test files.</li>
          <li>@gxp-risk HIGH|MEDIUM|LOW: Declares the risk level. RECOMMENDED on all test files.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Example source annotation:</t>
        <sourcecode type="typescript">
/**
 * @gxp-req REQ-001 "User authentication"
 * @gxp-spec SPEC-001-001 "OAuth2 PKCE flow"
 * @gxp-risk HIGH
 */
export async function authenticate(creds: Credentials) { /* ... */ }
        </sourcecode>
        <t>Example test annotation:</t>
        <sourcecode type="typescript">
/**
 * @gxp-spec SPEC-001-001
 * @trace US-001-001
 * @test-type OQ
 * @gxp-risk HIGH
 */
describe("OAuth2 PKCE login", () => { /* ... */ });
        </sourcecode>
        <t>The evidence generation pipeline MUST parse these annotations to route test results into the correct tiered package and to establish traceability from evidence back to specifications, user stories, and requirements.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="evidence_verification_protocol">
        <name>Evidence Verification Protocol</name>
        <t>A ROSIE-compliant system MUST implement a validatePackage operation that performs the following checks in order:</t>
        <ol>
          <li>Presence Check: Verify that manifest.json and signature.jws both exist in the package directory. If either is missing, the package is INVALID.</li>
          <li>Signature Verification: Decode signature.jws using the repository's public key (SPKI PEM, ES256). If the JWS signature is invalid or the key does not match, the package is INVALID.</li>
          <li>File Integrity: For each entry in manifest.files, verify the file exists at the declared relative path and its SHA-256 hash matches the declared value. Any mismatch indicates TAMPERING.</li>
          <li>Completeness Check: Enumerate all files in the package directory (excluding manifest.json and signature.jws). Any file not listed in the manifest indicates an UNAUTHORIZED ADDITION.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>A package passes validation if and only if all four checks succeed. The validatePackage operation MUST return a structured result containing a boolean valid flag and an array of error descriptions.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="evidence_lifecycle">
        <name>Evidence Lifecycle Management</name>
        <t>Evidence artifacts progress through a defined lifecycle:</t>
        <ol>
          <li>Generation: After test execution, the evidence generation pipeline collects test results, captures the environment snapshot, computes the system_state_hash, and creates a tiered evidence package directory.</li>
          <li>Manifest Creation: All files in the package are enumerated and hashed. A manifest.json is written with the complete file listing, total size, and file count.</li>
          <li>Signing: The manifest is signed using ES256 with the repository's private key. The resulting JWS compact serialization is written to signature.jws. Legacy JWS evidence artifacts (single-file .jws) MAY also be produced for backward compatibility.</li>
          <li>Verification: The validatePackage protocol (Section 6.4) is run immediately after signing to confirm the package was produced correctly. CI/CD pipelines MUST fail the build if verification fails.</li>
          <li>Archival: Evidence packages are committed to the repository under .gxp/evidence/ and uploaded as CI artifacts with a minimum retention of 90 days. For long-term compliance, evidence SHOULD be archived to durable storage (e.g., S3, R2) with write-once semantics.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>Evidence artifacts MUST NOT be modified after signing. If a test is re-run, a new evidence package MUST be created. The previous package remains in the repository as part of the historical record.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cryptography">
      <name>Cryptographic Evidence Protocol</name>
      <t>Validation evidence MUST be stored in .gxp/evidence/ as a JSON Web Signature (JWS) <xref target="RFC7515"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="signatures">
        <name>Signature Requirements</name>
        <t>The payload MUST include:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>system_state_hash: SHA-256 hash of the entire /src tree.</li>
          <li>test_results: Array of pass/fail status.</li>
          <li>timestamp: UTC ISO8601.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The JWS MUST be signed using a secure algorithm (e.g., ES256).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="system_state_hash">
        <name>System State Hash Computation</name>
        <t>The system_state_hash is a deterministic SHA-256 digest of the entire /src directory tree. It MUST be computed as follows:</t>
        <ol>
          <li>Recursively enumerate all files under /src, excluding node_modules/ and hidden directories (those starting with a dot).</li>
          <li>Sort the resulting file list by relative path (lexicographic, ascending) to ensure determinism across platforms.</li>
          <li>Initialize a SHA-256 hash context.</li>
          <li>For each file in sorted order, update the hash with the file's relative path (UTF-8), then update the hash with the file's binary content. Including the path detects file renames.</li>
          <li>Finalize the hash and encode as a 64-character lowercase hexadecimal string.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>The same system_state_hash computation MUST be used across all tiers (IQ, OQ, PQ) within a single validation run to ensure they attest to the same code state.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="adversarial">
        <name>Adversarial Agent Mitigation</name>
        <t>To prevent a single compromised agent from self-validating malicious code, a Multi-Party Authorization (MPA) model SHOULD be used. In HIGH risk systems, evidence artifacts SHOULD require signatures from at least two independent agent identities or one agent and one human validator.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document requests the registration of a new media type: application/rosie+json for ROSIE evidence artifacts.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="GXPMD">
          <front>
            <title>GxP.MD: Compliance Instructions for AI Coding Agents</title>
            <author fullname="James Gannon" surname="Gannon"/>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Version" value="2.1.0"/>
          <format type="TXT" target="https://gxp.md/spec"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="appendix_a">
      <name>Reference System Instruction</name>
      <t>Role: You are an Autonomous GxP Software Engineer operating under the ROSIE Framework (Regulated Object Structure for Intelligent Evidence). Your goal is to deliver software that is validated by design. If the project includes a GxP.MD file, that file is your primary compliance instruction set; this appendix provides baseline directives when no GxP.MD is present.</t>
      <t>Core Directives:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Read the State First: Always start by reading GxP.MD (if present) and .gxp/system_context.md.</li>
        <li>The V-Model is Law: Code MUST trace to a requirement and specification. In annotation-first mode (GxP.MD v2), @gxp-req and @gxp-spec annotations on the code itself satisfy this. In document-first mode, formal artifacts MUST exist before implementation begins.</li>
        <li>Traceability is Mandatory: Every source file and test MUST link to a requirement or spec ID via @gxp-req, @gxp-spec, @trace, and @test-type annotations.</li>
        <li>Risk Awareness: If changes impact data integrity or privacy, you MUST update the gxp_risk_rating and append to .gxp/risk_assessment.log.</li>
        <li>Evidence over Assurance: Verify that test outputs are captured as signed artifacts in .gxp/evidence/.</li>
        <li>Gate Compliance: Respect pre-commit, pre-merge, and per-release quality gates as defined in GxP.MD or project CI configuration.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="appendix_b">
      <name>Changelog</name>

      <section anchor="changelog_draft03">
        <name>draft-03 (2026-02-07)</name>
        <t>Changes from draft-02:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Abstract: Added reference to GxP.MD as the agent behavioral instruction layer.</li>
          <li>Section 3: Updated repository structure to include GxP.MD at project root. Made formal artifact directories (.gxp/requirements/, .gxp/user_stories/, .gxp/specs/) OPTIONAL when using annotation-first traceability.</li>
          <li>Section 3.2: Rewrote risk_assessment.log format from pipe-delimited single-line to Markdown with structured RISK-NNN entries (Date, Author, Component, Risk Level, Description, Impact, Mitigation, Status).</li>
          <li>Section 4.1: Updated validation_status enum values from DRAFT/VALIDATED/DEPRECATED to draft/in_review/validated/retired to align with GxP.MD v2.1.0.</li>
          <li>Section 5: Rewrote traceability to support both annotation-first (GxP.MD v2 model) and document-first (legacy model). Annotation-first is RECOMMENDED.</li>
          <li>Section 6.1: Renamed signature file from manifest.jws to signature.jws.</li>
          <li>Section 6.2: Aligned annotation tag names with GxP.MD v2.1.0: @gxp-tag → @gxp-spec, @gxp-criticality → @gxp-risk, @requirement → @gxp-req. Added source file annotation set. Removed @description (inline strings on @gxp-req and @gxp-spec replace it).</li>
          <li>Appendix A: Updated reference system instruction to reference GxP.MD as primary instruction set. Relaxed "NEVER write code without spec" to support annotation-first model. Added gate compliance directive.</li>
          <li>Added GxP.MD specification to informative references.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="changelog_draft02">
        <name>draft-02 (2026-02-05)</name>
        <t>Changes from draft-01:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Section 3: Added SS3.2 (Risk Assessment Log Format) defining the deterministic, append-only risk register format with required fields (DATE, RISK-ID, REQ-ID, Risk level, Impact, Mitigation, Test Coverage).</li>
          <li>Section 3: Added SS3.3 (Architecture Decision Records) specifying the .gxp/adr/ directory, ADR file naming convention, and required content (Title, Status, Context, Decision, Consequences).</li>
          <li>Section 6: Added SS6.2 (Evidence Package Format) defining the tiered directory-based evidence package structure with common files (metadata.json, environment.json, test-output.log, artifacts/test-results.json) and tier-specific content (IQ: dependency-tree + health-check; OQ: coverage-report; PQ: screenshots + traces).</li>
          <li>Section 6: Added SS6.3 (GxP Tag Annotation Syntax) defining @gxp-tag, @trace, @test-type, @gxp-criticality, @requirement, and @description annotations with REQUIRED/RECOMMENDED/OPTIONAL designation.</li>
          <li>Section 6: Added SS6.4 (Evidence Verification Protocol) specifying the four-step validatePackage operation (Presence Check, Signature Verification, File Integrity, Completeness Check).</li>
          <li>Section 6: Added SS6.5 (Evidence Lifecycle Management) defining the five-stage lifecycle (Generation, Manifest Creation, Signing, Verification, Archival) with immutability requirements.</li>
          <li>Section 7: Added SS7.2 (System State Hash Computation) specifying the deterministic SHA-256 algorithm for computing system_state_hash over the /src tree.</li>
          <li>Back matter: Added Appendix B (this changelog).</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="changelog_draft01">
        <name>draft-01 (2026-02-03)</name>
        <t>Initial publication. Established core framework: repository structure, apex document schema, traceability chain, verification tiering (IQ/OQ/PQ), cryptographic evidence protocol (JWS/ES256), security considerations, and reference system instruction.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
